A Guide to the York County (Va.) Records, 1722-1908
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
York County (Va.) Records, 1722-1908
The Library of Virginia
1046332, 1120205, 1120210, 1120213, 1120220, 1120226-1120227, 1120233, 1141502, 1154015-1154016, 1156337-1156338, 1160823 and 0007326998
11.15 cu. ft. (14 boxes and 1 folder)
York County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court records from York County.
Historical Information
York County originally was named Charles River County, for King Charles I, and was one of the eight shires, or counties, first enumerated in 1634. A record of 7 January 1634 employs the name York County, and a statute of 1643 officially changed the name to York County, probably in honor of James, duke of York, the second son of King Chares I, and later King James II.
Recognized in 1634 as an original shire. Most pre-Revolutionary War-era loose records are missing. Volumes that record deeds, court orders, and wills exist.
These records were also created by the County Court, the Superior Court of Law and the Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery.
Scope and Content
York County (Va.) Records, 1722-1908, consist of the following series: Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, County Administrative Records (including Board of Supervisors, Overseer of the Poor and Treasurer's Records), Court Records, Election Records, Fiduciary Records, Land Records, Marriage Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Public Buildings and Grounds, Road and Bridge Records, School Records, Tax and Fiscal Records and Wills.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional York County Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm" found on the Library of Virginia's web site.
Related Material
York County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional York Court Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Digital Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the Lost Records Localites Digital Collection available on Virginia Memory.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
York County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
Public records--Virginia--York County.
Geographical Names:
York County (Va.)--History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records--Virginia--York County.
Added Entry - Corporate Name:
York County (Va.) Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery.; York County (Va.) County Court.; York County (Va.) Superior Court of Law and Chancery.
Contents List
- Records 1772-1858
  Record Series: List of Tithables, ca.1790, List of tithables in that part of the City of Williamsburg lying in York county, 1792, 1794, 1795, 1796, 1801; Land Tax, 1846; Personal Property Tax, 1790-1794, 1843, 1849; County Clerk Bonds, 1772-74; Ended Causes, 1812, 1784; List of Voters, 1858; Judgment Buison v. Cabarrus, 1785.
- Records, 1793-1858
  Record Series: Bonds, Inventories & Appraisements, Accounts, Processioners Returns, Marriage Consents, Will
- Records, 1785-1879, undated
  Record Series: Court Records; Tax Assessment (1857); Also includes records pulled from judgments 1785-1829 including guardians' and trustees' accounts, wills, fiduciary records, tax and fiscal records, overseer of the poor records, marriage records, clerk's records, jury records and school records
- Records, 1784-1865
  Record Series: Committee/Curator Bonds(1791-1854), Guardian Bonds/Accts.(1787-1865); Minister Returns (1826), Bonds/Consents(1832-53); Misc. Bonds/Licenses(1784-1858)
- Records, 1760-1859
  Record Series: Common Law Papers(1760-1829), Wills(1813-1859), Bonds(1812-1837), Declarations(1776, 1782-1786). Box partially processed. Processed records are dated and foldered within this box.
- Records, 1760s-1908
  Record Series: Common Law Papers, Commonwealth Causes, Court Suits and Papers, courthouse repair accounts (1789-1790)
- Records, 1722-1860
  Record Series: Common Law Papers, Officials' Bonds, County Clerk's Bonds, other bonds
- Records, 1783-1888
  contains UNPROCESSED record series: Court and Suit Papers, Election Records, Bonds to Transport Oysters, Grand Jury Presentments, Officials' Bonds, Processioners' Returns, Reports of School Commissioners and Guardians' Accounts
- Records, 1733-1852
  Land Records: Oversized Deeds, 1758-1852; King George County Petition to break entail (Ad Quod Damnum), 1772; King William County Deed, 1733; Oversized Wills, 1777-1824; Court Records: Judgments: 1788, 1798 circa; Deed from Warwick County, 1841.
- Records, 1785-1829
  Common Law Papers and Judgments (is a partially processed collection from barcode 1120220.)
- Records, 1800-1900 circa
  Record Series: Oyster Bonds, Commonwealth Causes, School commissioner accounts (is a partially processed collection from barcode 1120220.)
- Records, 1777-1880
  Records Series: Court Records, 1780-1880; Marriage Records, 1812-1866; Miscellaneous Records, 1816, 1857; Fiduciary Records, 1784-1859; Public Buildings and Grounds, 1834-1835; Military and Pension Records, 1780, 1822; Wills, 1794, 1816-1818, 1827, 1830-1836, 1843; Overseer of the Poor Records, 1807-1828; Tax and Fiscal Records, 1785-1854; Land Records, 1785-1851; Road and Bridge Records, 1777-1854 and Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, 1777-1835.
- Records, 1788-1889
  Board of Supervisors' Records, 1872-1873; Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, 1799-1889; Court Records, 1788-1889; Election Records, 1846-1889; Fiduciary Records, 1807-1887; Marriage Records, 1823-1849; Land Records, 1799-1840 and Miscellaneous Records (Power of Attorney), 1842
- Records, 1823-1866
  Record Series: Bonds/Commissions/Oaths: Oaths of Election Officials, 1852-1866; Court Records: Judgments, Attachments, and Peace warrants, 1851; Election Records: Polls,1851-1859; Miscellaneous: Public Buildings and Grounds - Courthouse and Jail, 1823,1842,1853; Road and Bridge Records: Bridge Papers, 1851, 1857
- Records, 1782-1868
  Court Records, Fiduciary Records, Land Records, Marriage Records, Miscellaneous Records (notice of reorganization of York County Court) and Wills.